A Guide to the William W. Abbot Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- 1969-1971 UVA Faculty Senate- Meetings, 26 items (Box-folder 13:2)
  There are notes for Faculty Senate meetings. Of note are correspondence about Nominations for the Board of Visitors and a list of Administrative Committees, and notes about a proposed interdisciplinary University major.
- 1967-1977 UVA Graduate Committee, 54 items (Box-folder 13:3)
  Includes notes on courses relating to the Center for Textual and Editorial Studies, a revised report of the Graduate Program: Requirements, Regulations, and Procedures, a report of the Graduate Curriculum Revision Committee, notes regarding fellowships, a list of applicants for teaching positions in the history department, and a list of courses offered for history graduate students for the Fall 1973 semester.
- 1966-1973 UVA Department of History Curriculum, 40 items (Box-folder 13:4)
  Contains a Report on Student Representation, graduate courses offered in 1972-1973, requirements for history majors, notes on course registration, applicants and notes on teaching positions, papers on curriculum revision, and notes for Committee on M.A. Requirements and Related Matters.
- 1955-1972 UVA Department of History- Abbot, 41 items (Box-folder 13:5)
  Includes papers about Professor Abbot becoming Chairman of the department, history courses offered 1968-1969, report of The College Honors Program at the University of Virginia in 1968, report of The Graduate Program: Requirements, Regulations, and Procedures, and an Evaluation of the Corcoran History Department
- 1976-1991 UVA Department of History, 26 items (Box-folder 13:6)
  Includes Professor Abbot's report on his observations of the University of South Carolina's history department, the history department 1977 newsletter, correspondence about the search for a new associate professor, a proposal of a course evaluation system, and a request for Professor Abbot to continue to be on the Thomas Jefferson Fellows Committee.
- 1967-1971 UVA Library, 36 items (Box-folder 13:7)
  Includes correspondence relating to book orders and research needs of the history department, departmental library funds allocations, and a report of the Library Committee on recommendations for improvement and the library's current state.
- 1970-1973; 1985 UVA Library, 48 items (Box-folder 13:8)
  Includes reports about the library to the Board of Visitors, reports of the University Library Committee, 1970-1971 Annual Report for the University Library, a Library Space Proposal for expanding the library facilities, and a report of the Need for a Science-Technology Library and Information Center.
- 1967 UVA- NDEA Institute, 5 items (Box-folder 14:1)
  Includes information and a proposal for the 1967 Summer NDEA Institute in US History.
- 1966-1969 Papers of George Mason, 9 items (Box-folder 14:2)
  Includes minutes of the meeting of the Administrative Board for the Papers of George Mason and the 1966 Annual Report.
- 1966-1977 Papers of George Washington, 45 items (Box-folder 14:3)
  Contains the 1977 Annual Report, proposal for a comprehensive edition of the Papers of George Washington and the report from the University committee about it, recommendations from various editors of similar papers (including Julian P. Boyd of the Thomas Jefferson Papers and L.H. Butterfield of the Adams Papers), the progress reports of these respective papers, and an article from the Washington Post about editing the George Washington Papers.
- 1968; 1989 Papers of George Washington, 18 items (Box-folder 14:4)
  Includes a proposed budget for the Washington Papers, recommendations from editors of similar papers, correspondence with the Mount Vernon Ladies Association of the Union concerning their grant for the editing of the Washington Papers, and notes on the conference "George Washington and the Virginia Backcountry" in 1989.
- 1963; 1967-1968 Papers of James Monroe, 11 items (Box-folder 14:5)
  Includes notes on the James Monroe Papers Conference, a paper on the James Monroe Materials by the National Historical Publications Commission, and a suvery of the James Monroe Papers by William Ray.
- 1966-1968 University of Virginia Press, 49 items (Box-folder 14:6)
  Includes reports for 1966, 1967, and 1968, meeting minutes of the Board of Directors, and reviews of books and manuscripts.
- 1969-1988 University of Virginia Press, 50 items (Box-folder 14:7)
  Includes a report for 1969, meeting minutes of the Board of Directors, a report ( the University Press Since 1962,) and notes on books and manuscripts.
- 1966-1968; n.d. University of Virginia Press- Manuscripts, 22 items (Box-folder 14:8)
  Includes reviews of manuscripts, the text of Pat H. Butler's manuscript This World and the Next in Old Deerfield, and a proposal for the Writing of a History of Virginia Since 1865.
- 1972-1983 UVA Public Occasions Committee (Founder's Day and Finals), 80 items (Box-folder 15:1)
  Includes meeting minutes and notes on Founder's Day and Finals for 1973-1984.
- 1966-1974 UVA Virginia Quarterly Review, 39 items (Box-folder 15:2)
  Includes the 1970 and 1972-1974 Annual Reports, notes on the Emily Clark Balch Contest, and correspondence about searching for a new editor in 1973-1974.
- 1975-1989 UVA Virginia Quarterly Review, 41 items (Box-folder 15:3)
  Includes notes on the Emily Clark Balch Contest, the 1976, 1977, 1979, 1981, and 1982 Annual Reports, and the Board of the VQR meeting notes.
- 1967-1974 UVA Sesquicentennial of the University, 18 items (Box-folder 15:4)
  Includes notes from the Visiting Scholars Subcommittee on their program and notes from the Sesquicentennial Associate Selection Committee for the Associateship Program.
- 1973-1974 Sesquicentennial Associateships of the Center for Advanced Studies, 13 items (Box-folder 15:5)
  Includes notes from the Sesquicentennial Associateships Program for 1974-1975 and 1975-1976.
- 1967-1968 UVA Scholars Committee- Visiting Scholars for Sesquicentennial Program, 83 items (Box-folder 15:6)
  Includes nominations for visiting scholars, notes about proposed minor changes to the program, and comments on possible scholars.
- 1966; 1970-1975 Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission- Virginia Center for Archaeology, 51 items (Box-folder 15:7)
  Includes meeting minutes of the Advisory Committee on the Virginia Research Center for Historical Archaeology, a report of the Archaeology Program at the College of William and Mary, a resolution to protect the site of the remains of a Revolutionary War shipwreck and a related Survey Report, and a bill proposal about underwater historic preservation.
- 1979-1983 Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission- Virginia Center for Archaeology, 54 items (Box-folder 16:1)
  Includes a report on the Organization and Methods Study of the Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission, meeting minutes of the Advisory Committee, VCRA 1980 and 1982 Newsletters, a report on the Virginia Research Center for Archaeology in the 1980's, and a report of Evaluation: Historic Landmarks Commission Proposal to Reorganize its Survey and Planning Function.
- 1976 Virginia Research Center for Archaeology, Part 1 of 2 43 items (Box-folder 16:2)
  Includes meeting minutes of the Advisory Committee, a bill proposal about underwater historic preservation, a report from the Council of Virginia Archaeologists, newspaper articles about excavation sites around Virginia (including a shipwreck in the York River,) a progress report for a Gloucester County site, and forms to register sites as National Historic Places.
- 1977-1978 Virginia Research Center for Archaeology, Part 2 of 2 37 items (Box-folder 16:3)
  Includes a report on the State of the Virginia Research Center for Archaeology 1976-1977 and meeting minutes from the Advisory Committee.
- 1978-1984 Virginia Society of History Teachers, 28 items (Box-folder 16:4)
  Includes plans and notes on the 1978-1984 Virginia Society of History Teachers conferences.
- 1962-1975 John Wiley & Sons Publisher, 83 items (Box-folder 16:5)
  Correspondence and notes about Professor Abbot's volume on Colonial America for the American Republic series.
- 1969 Winterthur Program in Early American Culture Conference, 7 items (Box-folder 16:6)
  Correspondence about the Winterthur Program in Early American Culture Conference in October 1969.
- 1965-1966 William and Mary, 9 items (Box-folder 16:7)
  Includes a proposal and report for a PhD History program at the College of William and Mary and notes about the history course The Literature of Recent American History.
- 1983-1984 Articles- "Low Country Back Country", 3 items (Box-folder 17:1)
  Correspondence and notes about Professor Abbot's article "Low Country Back Country." Also includes the text of this article.
- 1962; 1971-1994 Financial Records, 70 items (Box-folder 17:2)
  Financial records for conference and research related expenses.
- 1958-1966 Financial Records, 28 items (Box-folder 17:3)
  Financial records relating to travel for work, salary, and personal expenses.
- 1971-1973 Grant Proposals, 20 items (Box-folder 17:4)
  Professor Abbot's reviews of papers and evaluations of grant proposals. Several grant proposals are also included.
- 1985-1992 Invitations, 6 items (Box-folder 17:5)
  Invitations to various historical and personal celebrations.
- 1960 Lecture Notes, 18 items (Box-folder 17:6)
  Notes for Constitutional History lecture course in 1960.
- 1960 Lecture Notes, 32 items (Box-folder 17:7)
  Notes for Virginia History lecture course in 1960.
- 1959 Lecture Notes, 19 items (Box-folder 17:8)
  Notes for American Revolution lecture course in 1959.
- n.d. Lecture Notes, 41 items (Box-folder 17:9)
  Notes for History 202 lecture course.
- 1960; n.d. Lecture Notes, 30 items (Box-folder 17:10)
  Included are assorted notes on early Virginia history for the Revolutionary War History lecture courses
- n.d. Lecture Notes, 18 items (Box-folder 17:11)
  Notes for History 201 lecture course.
- n.d. Lecture Notes, 18 items (Box-folder 18:1)
- n.d. Lecture Notes, 48 items (Box-folder 18:2)
  Notes on various lecture topics, including events leading up to the American Revolution.
- n.d. Lecture Notes, 39 items (Box-folder 18:3)
  Notes on various lecture topics, including events leading up to the American Revolution and how historians view the Revolution now.
- n.d. Lecture Notes, 15 items (Box-folder 18:4)
  Notes on events leading up to the American Revolution.
- 1966-1989 Legal, 27 items (Box-folder 18:5)
  Legal documents including a publishing agreement for Professor Abbot to be Editor-in-Chief of the George Washington Encyclopedia, a letter from the White House about the newly established American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, and a letter offering Professor Abbot the position of James Madison Professor of American History at UVA.
- 18 July 1986 Manuscript- Dumas Malone, 1 item (Box-folder 18:6)
  Typescript of the manuscript" My Long Journey with Mr. Jefferson" by Dumas Malone.
- n.d. Manuscript- Abbot, 1 item (Box-folder 18:7)
  Typescript of William Abbot's manuscript "The Colonial Beginnings of the United States, 1607-1763."
- 1966-1974 Manuscripts- Abbot, 31 items (Box-folder 19:1)
  Correspondence about publishing Professor Abbot's manuscripts.
- 1963; 1965-1966 Manuscripts- Abbot (American History Text), 12 items (Box-folder 19:2)
  Correspondence about revisions and publishing Professor Abbot's manuscript.
- 1966-1971 Manuscripts- Paul Taylor Correspondence, 47 items (Box-folder 19:3)
  Correspondence about Paul Taylor's manuscript "Georgia Plan: 1732-1752"
- 1966; 1974-1977 Newspaper Clippings, 10 items (Box-folder 19:4)
  Included are newspaper clippings about Professor Abbot and his colleagues.
- 10 March 1971; n.d. Papers, 3 items (Box-folder 19:5)
  Papers titled, "Religion and the Republic: The Search for Religious Liberty in a Christian Commonwealth, 1776-1854" by W. G. McLoughlin and "The Legitimizing of Violence in the Revolutionary Era: The American Revolution and American Violence" by Richard Maxwell Brown (including comments from Professor Abbot).
- 1 March 1962; 1 February 1971; n d. Papers, 9 items (Box-folder 19:6)
  Includes papers by Jack P. Greene, Richard Maxwell Brown, and William Abbot.
- 1966-1969; n.d. Student Papers, 8 items (Box-folder 19:7)
  Includes papers by Charlyn Ryll, Patricia Molen, Gary Lord, Robert A. Murdock, James L. Anderson, James E. Chrismer, and E.D. Robertson.
- 1967-1968 Student Papers, 13 items (Box-folder 20:1)
  Includes papers by William B. Bedford, Donald S. Spencer, Steven H. Hochman, Richard E. Ellis, Charlyn Ryll, Judy Wellman, Carl S. Matthews, and John B. Boles.
- 1989-1992 Retirement, 5 items (Box-folder 20:2)
  Documents relating to Professor Abbot's retirement. Includes a letter from the Board of Visitors electing Professor Abbot to Professor Emeritus.
- 1970-1971 Readers Reports, 15 items (Box-folder 20:3)
  Appraisal requests for manuscripts and Professor Abbot's recommendations.
- 1962-1976 Reviews, 89 items (Box-folder 20:4)
  Professor Abbot's reviews of articles, papers, books, and project proposals
- 1963-1966; n.d. Reviews, 27 items (Box-folder 20:5)
- 1967-1969 Reviews, 52 items (Box-folder 20:6)
  Professor's Abbot's reviews of articles, papers, books, and project proposals
- 1977-1982 Reviews, 74 items (Box-folder 21:1)
  Professor Abbot's reviews of articles, papers, books, and project proposals.
- 1966-1968; 1982; n.d. Speeches, 29 items (Box-folder 21:2)
  Includes correspondence about up-coming speeches and typed and handwritten scripts for speeches about the George Washington Papers, the article "Lowcountry, Backcountry: Georgia in the American Revolution," and Professor Abbot's views on the study of history.
- 1962 Vitas, 5 items (Box-folder 21:3)
  Professor Abbot's vitas and project proposal for researching post-American Revolutionary South Carolina, dating from his time at Rice University.
- Confidential
  - 1976 Dean of Afro-American Affairs and Assistant Provost, 4 items (Box-folder 22:1)
    Correspondence and report relating to the search for a new Dean of Afro-American Affairs and Assistant Provost.
  - January-June 1973 Nomination of the New President- Faculty Senate Committee, Part 1 of 2 24 items (Box-folder 22:2)
    Report on Nomination of a President, meeting minutes of the Faculty Senate, correspondence between members of the Nominating Committee, and notes and views about the duties and requirements of the next President.
  - May-October 1973 Nomination of the President- Faculty Senate Committee, Part 2 of 2 9 items (Box-folder 22:3)
    Reports from the Faculty Senate Committee and the Student Committee on Nomination of a President, report on the nominees for President from the Special Committee of the Faculty Senate, and the formal nomination of Frank Hereford, Jr. for President.
  - 1981-1984 Faculty Senate Committee on Faculty Relations, 54 items (Box-folder 22:4)
    Correspondence and reports relating to issues of conflict within the Faculty and Annual Reports of the Senate Committee on Faculty Relations for 1981-1983.
  - September-October 1969 Faculty Senate, 3 items (Box-folder 22:5)
    Reports relating to the proposal to allow student representation at Faculty meetings
  - 1966-1967; 1969 Grades, 15 items (Box-folder 22:6)
    Grades of students in Professor Abbot's history courses
  - 1973-1974 Students' Grades and Grievances, 4 items (Box-folder 22:7)
    Correspondence between students and Professor Abbot about grades and requests to continue to the doctorate level of study in history
  - October-November 1969 Afeworki Paulos, 2 items (Box-folder 22:8)
    Correspondence regarding an accusation of racial prejudice in the George Washington Papers
  - 1980-1981 UVA Promotions History Department, 57 items (Box-folder 22:9)
    Reports and correspondence relating to the promotion to tenured associate professor of history department faculty members
  - n.d. Graduate Committee, 2 items (Box-folder 22:10)
    Scores of new and resident students
  - 1972; 1974 Hires, 3 items (Box-folder 22:11)
    Recommendations for candidates to hire
  - October 1987 UVA History Department Promotions- Dorothy Ross, 14 items (Box-folder 22:12)
    Correspondence and reports relating to the promotion of Dorothy Ross to professor of history
  - 1987-1988 UVA Committee to Nominate the History Department Chair, 31 items (Box-folder 22:13)
    Correspondence regarding the nomination of the History Department chair and recommendations for promotions to full professorship of History Department faculty members.
  - November-December 1996 Library of Virginia, 1 item (Box-folder 22:14)
    Correspondence between Professor Abbot and the administration at the Library of Virginia recommending that the Library keep its archives with the Library instead of separating them
  - 1962; 1968-1975 UVA Promotion Committee, 30 items (Box-folder 22:15)
    Correspondence regarding promotions in the History Department and in the College of Arts and Sciences as a whole
- Confidential
  - 1967-1993 Recommendations Abraham-Ayres, 17 items (Box-folder 23:1)
  - 1960-1991 Recommendations Babin-Boylan, 68 items (Box-folder 23:2)
  - 1961-1993 Recommendations Bradford-Bynum, 51 items (Box-folder 23:3)
  - 1958-1993 Recommendations Calabrese-Cunningham, 58 items (Box-folder 23:4)
  - 1964-1989 Recommendations Dauer-Evans, 60 items (Box-folder 23:5)
  - 1957-1991 Recommendations Fairbanks-Friend, 21 items (Box-folder 23:6)
  - 1964-1997 Recommendations Garrett-Guzinski, 60 items (Box-folder 23:7)
- Confidential
  - 1956-1989 Recommendations Hackett-Hemphill, 58 items (Box-folder 24:1)
  - 1962-1990 Recommendations Henderson-Howell, 33 items (Box-folder 24:2)
  - 1972-1978 Recommendations Ingram-Isaac, 13 items (Box-folder 24:3)
  - 1962-1980 Recommendations Jackson-Jordan, 32 items (Box-folder 24:4)
  - 1959-1987 Recommendations Kasta-Kukla, 60 items (Box-folder 24:5)
  - 1969-1990 Recommendations Lacy-Lorish, 29 items (Box-folder 24:6)
  - 1964-1991 Recommendations Malone-Musson, 76 items (Box-folder 24:7)
  - 1964-1992 Recommendations Nardini-Onuf, 13 items (Box-folder 24:8)
  - 1956-1992 Recommendations Pagnani-Putnam, 50 items (Box-folder 24:9)
- Confidential
  - 1955-1986 Recommendations Ragsdale-Rutman, 37 items (Box-folder 25:1)
  - 1961-1990 Recommendations Salerno-Smith, Canfield, 26 items (Box-folder 25:2)
  - 1957-1992 Recommendations Smith, Daniel-Swanson, 80 items (Box-folder 25:3)
  - 1958-1993 Recommendations Taishoff-Votto, 48 items (Box-folder 25:4)
  - 1958-1989 Recommendations Wade-Wehtje, 48 items (Box-folder 25:5)
  - 1964-1989 Recommendations Wellman-Wood, 30 items (Box-folder 25:6)
  - 1968-1993 Recommendations Young-Yuhnke, 40 items (Box-folder 25:7)
  - 1965-1973 Requests for Recommendations, 4 items (Box-folder 25:8)
    Requests from institutions for recommendations to fill positions.
  - 1962-1971 Recommendations Unknown, 4 items (Box-folder 25:9)
- Confidential
  - 1954-1965 Roll Books, 8 items (Box-folder 26:1)
    List of enrolled students and their grades.
  - 1955-1962 Roll Books, 8 items (Box-folder 26:2)
  - April 1967 NDEA Salary, 2 items (Box-folder 26:3)
    Professor Abbot's salary for NDEA History Institute
  - 1963-1966 Salary, 5 items (Box-folder 26:4)
    Professor Abbot's salary at the College of William and Mary
  - 1978 Salary Institute of Early American History and Culture, 2 items (Box-folder 26:5)
    Report of salaries at the Institute of Early American History and Culture
  - 1970-1971 Sesquicentennial Associate Selection Committee, 6 items (Box-folder 26:6)
    Correspondence amongst the Selection Committee for the faculty awards for 1971-1973.
  - 1971-1972 Sesquicentennial Selection Committee, 2 items (Box-folder 26:7)
    Correspondence relating to the Sesquicentennial faculty awards for 1972-1973.
  - 1980-1981 UVA Search Committee for the Dean of the Faculty, 38 items (Box-folder 26:8)
    Correspondence of the committee charged with finding the successor to Edwin E. Floyd, Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences. Committee members include William W. Abbot, Jeanne C. Biggar, Hugh M. Davidson, Robert H. Kretsinger, and Richard T. Selden, Willard W. Harrison, and Audrey D. Jordan. President Frank L. Hereford is also a correspondent
  - 1968-1969; n.d. Graded student papers, 5 items (Box-folder 26:9)